Section on Neurology and Psychiatry Records
Section on Neurology and Psychiatry Records.
1885-1984
New York Academy of Medicine. Section on Neurology and Psychiatry.
1.2 linear feet; 1 carton
Mss.arc
New York Academy of Medicine Library. Rare Book Room.
Historical Note
The Section on Neurology of the New York Academy of Medicine was established in 1885. In 1897 the section was expanded to include psychiatry. In 1932 some of the psychiatrists petitioned to have a separate section, but the Academy's council decided against the change. In the early 1970s the question of separate sections came up again and this time it was decided to have a section on neurological sciences and a section on psychiatry.
Scope and Content
This collection, which may not be complete at the moment, is particularly interesting. The section's membership included members of the several other groups devoted to neurology and psychiatry whose records are in the possession of the Academy. The membership of the Schilder Society and the Salmon Committee seldom overlapped, but many of the members of both those groups appear in the section records.
Of special interest are the transcripts of the meetings of the section during the 1930s. A regular number of these meetings were combined meetings with the New York Neurological Society. For the most part the minutes in this collection simply record the topics presented and the names of the speakers and discussers. The transcripts record the full content, and were submitted to 2 journals. Another area of interest are the files related to the attempt in the 1930s to have a separate section on psychiatry, an effort that failed. By 1972 the separation was made.
This inventory identifies the records as they reflect the various forms in which this section functioned.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the catalog of The New York Academy of Medicine Library. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Neurology -- New York (State) -- New York.; Neurology -- Societies, etc.; Psychiatry -- New York (State) -- New York.; Psychiatry -- Societies, etc.; New York Academy of Medicine. Section on Neurology and Psychiatry.; New York Academy of Medicine. Section on Neurology.; New York Academy of Medicine. Section on Neurosciences.; New York Academy of Medicine. Section on Psychiatry.
Container List
- Section on Neurology, Series 1
  - Minutes, 1885-1928. (Box 1)
- Section on Neurology and Psychiatry, Series 2
  - Minutes
    - Minutes, 1885-1928. (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 1931-1940, 1961-1962. (Box 1)
    - Transcripts of Meetings, 1932-1937. (Box 1)
    - Minutes of the Advisory Committee, 1931, 1932. (Box 1)
    - Minutes of the Executive Session, 1940. (Box 1)
    - Minutes of the Committee on Sections, 1937. (Box 1)
    - Annual Report to Council, 1921-1926. (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Text of Discussion, 1936, 1937. (Box 1)
  - Executive Working Papers
    - Correspondence of Byron Stookey, Chairman, 1933. (Box 1)
    - Correspondence of Clarence P. Oberndorf, Secretary, 1932-1933. (Box 1)
    - Correspondence of Clarence P. Oberndorf, Chairman, 1933-1934. (Box 1)
    - Correspondence of C. Burns Craig, Secretary, 1933-1934 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence of A. A. Brill, Secretary, 1935-1936 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence of A. A. Brill, Chairman, 1936-1937. (Box 1)
    - Correspondence of Irving Pardee, Secretary, 1936-1937. (Box 1)
    - Correspondence of Samuel Brock, Secretary, 1940. (Box 1)
    - Papers re: Proposal to establish a separate section on Psychiatry, 1931-1932. (Box 1)
    - Papers re: Separating psychiatry from neurology, 1931-1932. (Box 1)
    - Papers re: Creating 2 sections ie. psychiatry and neurosciences, 1967-1972. (Box 1)
    - Meeting/Program Schedules, 1926-1951. (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Papers, 1931-1939, 1944-1948. (Box 1)
  - Membership
    - Qualifications for Members and Fellows, 1931-1933. (Box 1)
    - Attendance Lists, 1923-1931. (Box 1)
    - Section Members / Mailing Lists, 1933, 1968-1970. (Box 1)
    - Member / Mailing List re: NY Neurological Society, 1969-1970. (Box 1)
  - Publicity
    - Program Announcements, 1923-1984. (Box 1)
    - Invitation to Reception, 1925. (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Programs of Neurological Society, 1932, 1933. (Box 1)
    - Bulletin of the New York Academy of Medicine, 1987. (Box 1)
    - Directory of the Nassau Neuropsychiatric Society, 1967. (Box 1)
    - Reprints from the Journal of General Pscyhology, 1949, 1953. (Box 1)
    - Flyers re: Annie Lord, 1933. (Box 1)
- Section on Psychiatry, Series 3
  - Correspondence, 1971-1972. (Box 1)
  - Member/Mailing List, 1972. (Box 1)
  - Program Announcements, 1981, 1984. (Box 1)
- Section on Neurological Sciences, Series 4
  - Member/Mailing List, 1972-1976. (Box 1)
Additional Resources
An officer list is available.